It's very, very difficult
Es muy difícil hablar,
to speak at the end of a conference like this,
al final de una conferencia como esta.
because everyone has spoken. Everything has been said.
Todo el mundo ha hablado. Todo está dicho.
So I thought that what may be useful is to remind us
He pensado que lo más útil será recordar
of some of the things that have gone on here,
alguna de las cosas que se han dicho aquí.
and then maybe offer some ideas which we can take away,
Así podemos extraer ideas
and take forward and work on.
en las que trabajar y sacar adelante.
That's what I'd like to try and do.
Eso es lo que quiero intentar hacer.
We came here saying we want to talk about "Africa: the Next Chapter."
Vinimos para hablar de "África: el siguiente capítulo"
But we are talking about "Africa: the Next Chapter" because we are looking at the old and the present chapter -- that we're looking at,
Pero al hablar de "África: el siguiente capítulo": miramos al pasado y al presente. Lo vemos y
and saying it's not such a good thing.
decimos que no fue muy bueno.
The picture I showed you before, and this picture, of drought, death and disease
Estas fotos que muestran sequías, muertes y enfermedades
is what we usually see.
es lo que solemos ver.
What we want to look at is "Africa: the Next Chapter," and that's this: a healthy, smiling, beautiful African.
Pero queremos ver "África: el siguiente capítulo". que tiene la cara de un africano sano, sonriente y guapo.
And I think it's worth remembering what we've heard
Creo que es importante recordar lo que hemos oído
through the conference right from the first day,
en la conferencia desde el primer día,
where I heard that all the important statistics have been given --
donde se dieron las estadísticas
about where we are now,
del momento actual
about how the continent is doing much better.
y de lo mucho que ha mejorado el continente.
And the importance of that is that we have a platform to build on.
Lo importante es que tenemos una plataforma sobre la que construir.
So I'm not going to spend too much time --
Así que no perderé mucho tiempo
just to show you, refresh your memories
en haceros recordar que
that we are here for "Africa: the Next Chapter" because for the first time there really is a platform to build on.
estamos aquí por el siguiente capítulo, ya que es la primera vez que tenemos una plataforma sobre la que construir.
We really do have it going right
Realmente tenemos una posibilidad,
that the continent is growing at rates that people had thought would not happen.
el continente está creciendo a un ritmo inimaginable.
After decades of 2 percent, we are now at 5 percent,
Décadas después, hemos pasado del 2 al 5 por ciento
and it's going to -- projected -- 6 and 7 percent even.
y se estima que pasaremos al 6 o incluso al 7 por ciento.
And inflation has come down.
La inflación ha disminuido.
External debt -- something that I can tell you a long story about
La deuda externa, de la que tengo mucho que contar
because I personally worked on one of the biggest debts on the continent --
pues trabajé en una de las deudas más grandes del continente,
has come down dramatically.
ha descendido drásticamente.
You know, as you can see,
Como pueden ver aquí ha descendido
from almost 50 billion down to about 12 or 13 billion.
de 50 billones a 12 o 13 billones.
Now this is a huge achievement.
Esto es un gran logro.
You know, we've built up reserves. Why is that important?
Hemos acumulado reservas. ¿Y por qué es importante?
It's because it shows off our economies, shows off our currencies
Porque respalda a nuestras economías y monedas
and gives a platform on which people can plan and build, including businesses.
y nos da la plataforma para construir y crear empresas.
We've also seen some evidence that all this is making a difference
También vemos indicios de que todo esto está marcando la diferencia,
because private investment flows have increased.
pues la inversión privada ha aumentado.
I want to remind you again -- I know you saw these statistics before --
Quisiera volver a recordarles... Sé que ya han visto estas estadísticas.
from almost 6 billion we are now at about 18 billion.
Hemos pasado de 6 a 18 billones.
In 2005, remittances -- I just took one country, Nigeria
En 2005, sólo en Nigeria, las transferencias
skyrocketing -- skyrocketing is too dramatic,
como ven la subida es espectacular
but increasing dramatically.
y continúa aumentando drásticamente.
And in many other countries this is happening.
Esto también ocurre en muchos otros países.
Why is this important? Because it shows confidence.
¿Por qué es importante? Demuestra confianza.
People are now confident to bring --
Ahora la geste confía y trae...
if your people in the diaspora bring their money back,
Si su gente en la diáspora trae el dinero,
it shows other people that, look,
demuestra a otros que, miren,
there is emerging confidence in your country.
hay una confianza emergente en tu país.
And instead of an outflow, you are now getting a net inflow.
y así, el dinero en lugar de salir comienza a entrar.
Now, why is all this important, to have to go really fast?
¿Por qué es importante hacerlo tan rápido?
It's important that we build this platform, that we have the president, Kikwete, and others of our leaders who are saying,
Construir la plataforma es importante, y escuchar al presidente Kikwete y otros líderes que dicen:
"Look, we must do something different."
"Tenemos que hacer algo diferente"
Because we are confronted with a challenge.
porque nos enfrentamos a un reto.
62 percent of our population is below the age of 24.
El 62 por ciento de la población tiene menos de 24 años.
What does this mean?
¿Qué significa esto?
This means that we have to focus on how our youth are going to be engaged in productive endeavor in their lives.
Que tenemos que centrarnos en cómo la juventud se involucrará de forma productiva en la vida.
You have to focus on how to create jobs,
Centrémonos en cómo crear empleo,
make sure they don't fall into disease, and that they get an education.
en que no enfermen y en su educación.
But most of all that they are productively engaged in life,
Y sobre todo, en que hagan algo provechoso en la vida
and that they are creating the kind of productive environment
y en que crean un ambiente productivo
in our countries that will make things happen.
en nuestros países, que hará que las cosas cambien.
And to support this, I just recently --
Para apoyar esta causa, una de las cosas
one of the things I've done since leaving government
que he hecho tras dejar el gobierno
is to start an opinion research organization in Nigeria.
es fundar una organización de estudios de opinión pública en Nigeria.
Most of our countries don't even have any opinion research.
La mayoría de los países no tiene estudios de opinión.
People don't have voice.
La gente no tiene voz.
There is no way you can know what people want.
No hay forma de saber lo que quieren.
One of the things we asked them recently was what's their top issue.
Les preguntamos qué era lo que más les preocupaba.
Like in every other country where this has been done,
Y al igual que en el resto de países,
jobs is the top issue.
el trabajo es la primera preocupación.
I want to leave this up here and come back to it.
Me detendré aquí para luego retomarlo.
But before I get to this slide, I just wanted to run you through this.
Antes de ver esta diapo quiero contarles algo.
And to say that for me, the next stage of building this platform
Para mí, el siguiente paso tras construir la plataforma,
that now enables us to move forward --
que hoy nos permite avanzar
and we mustn't make light of it.
y a la que no hay que restarle importancia.
It was only 5, 6, 7 years ago
Hace apenas 5, 6, o 7 años,
we couldn't even talk about the next chapter, because we were in the old chapter.
ni podíamos hablar del siguiente capítulo pues estábamos en el anterior.
We were going nowhere.
Íbamos hacia ninguna parte.
The economies were not growing.
Nuestras economías no crecían.
We were having negative per capita growth.
El crecimiento per capita era negativo
The microeconomic framework and foundation for moving forward
El marco microeconómico y los cimientos para salir adelante
was not even there.
no existían.
So let's not forget that it's taken a lot to build this,
No olvidemos que ha costado mucho construir esto,
including all those things that we tried to do in Nigeria that Dele referred to.
incluidas las cosas que intentamos hacer en Nigeria.
Creating our own program to solve problems, like fighting corruption,
Implantamos un programa para solucionar problemas como la corrupción,
building institutions, stabilizing the micro economy. So now we have this platform we can build on.
creamos instituciones y estabilizamos la microeconomía. Por eso tenemos esta plataforma para construir.
And it brings us to the debate that has been going on here:
Esto nos lleva al debate que se ha mantenido aquí:
aid versus private sector, aid versus trade, etc.
ayuda frente al sector privado, frente al comercio, etc.
And someone stood up to say that one of the frustrating things
Alguien alzó la voz y dijo que era frustrante
is that it's been a simplistic debate. And that's not what the debate should be about.
la simplicidad del debate. Y que el debate no debería ser así.
That's engaging in the wrong debate.
Sería participar en el debate equivocado.
The issue here is how do we get a partnership that involves government donors,
El tema aquí es cómo crear una sociedad entre donantes gubernamentales
the private sector and ordinary African people
el sector privado y ciudadanos africanos,
taking charge of their own lives?
que tomen las riendas de su vida.
How do we combine all this?
¿Cómo se combina todo esto?
To move our continent forward, to do the things that need doing
para salir adelante y hacer las cosas necesarias
that I talked about -- getting young people employed.
de las que os hablé antes. Los jóvenes tienen que trabajar.
Getting the creative juices flowing on this continent,
Tiene que fluir la salvia creativa del continente
much of what you have seen here.
y hemos podido ver mucha de ella aquí.
So I'm afraid we've been engaging a little bit in the wrong debate.
Así que creo que nos hemos equivocado de debate.
We need to bring it back to say,
Es necesario que se vuelvan a preguntar
what is the combination of all these factors
¿qué combinación de factores
that is going to yield what we want? (Applause)
nos permitirá conseguir lo que queremos? (Aplausos)
And I want to tell you something.
Les voy a contar una cosa.
For me, the issue about aid --
Para mí las ayudas...
I don't think that Africans need to now go all the way over to the other side
No creo que los africanos tengan que irse al otro extremo
and feel bad about aid.
y sentirse mal por las ayudas.
Africa has been giving the other countries aid.
África ha estado dando ayudas a otros países.
Mo Ibrahim said at a debate we were at that
Mo Ibrahim dijo en un debate que
he dreams one day when Africa will be giving aid.
el sueña con el día que África ofrezca ayudas.
And I said, "Mo, you're right. We have -- no, but we've already been doing it!
Y yo le dije, "Mo, tienes razón... pero ya lo hemos estado haciendo!
The U.K. and the U.S. could not have been built today without Africa's aid." (Applause)
El Reino Unido y EEUU no podrían haberse construido sin la ayuda de África." (Aplausos)
It is all the resources that were taken from Africa,
Gracias a todos los recursos extraídos de África,
including human, that built these countries today!
también humanos, se han construido estos países.
So when they try to give back, we shouldn't be on the defensive.
Por lo que si quieren devolver algo, no deberíamos ofendernos.
The issue is not that.
No deberíamos discutir eso.
The issue is how are we using what has been given back.
La discusión es cómo utilizar aquello que nos devuelven.
How are we using it?
¿Cómo lo estamos utilizando?
Is it being directed effectively?
¿Se está utilizando con eficacia?
I want to tell you a little story.
Os quiero contar una historia.
Why I don't mind if we get aid, but we use it well.
El porqué acepto la ayuda si la usamos bien.
From 1967 to '70, Nigeria fought a war -- the Nigeria-Biafra war.
Entre 1967 y 1970 Nigeria vivió la guerra de Biáfara.
And in the middle of that war, I was 14 years old.
A mediados de la guerra tenía 14 años.
We spent much of our time with my mother cooking.
Pasábamos casi todo el tiempo cocinando junto a mi madre.
For the army -- my father joined the army as a brigadier -- the Biafran army. We were on the Biafran side.
Para el ejército, mi padre era un brigadier del ejército de Biáfra. Estábamos del lado de Biáfra.
And we were down to eating one meal a day, running from place to place,
Sólo comíamos una vez al día, íbamos de un sitio a otro,
but wherever we could help we did.
y ayudábamos en lo que podíamos.
At a certain point in time, in 1969, things were really bad.
En un momento dado, en 1969, las cosas iban muy mal.
We were down to almost nothing in terms of a meal a day.
Casi no nos quedaba nada, en relación a la comida.
People, children were dying of kwashiorkor.
Los niños morían de Kwashiorkor.
I'm sure some of you who are not so young
Estoy segura de que los menos jóvenes
will remember those pictures.
recordaréis aquellas fotografías.
Well, I was in the middle of it.
Pues bien, yo estaba en medio de todo eso.
In the midst of all this, my mother fell ill with a stomach ailment for two or three days. We thought she was going to die.
Entre tanto mi madre enfermó del estómago dos o tres días. Pensamos que se iba a morir.
My father was not there.
Mi padre no estaba allí.
He was in the army.
Estaba en el ejército.
So I was the oldest person in the house.
Yo era la más mayor de la casa.
My sister fell very ill with malaria.
Mi hermana enfermó gravemente de malaria.
She was three years old and I was 15.
Ella tenía 3 años y yo 15.
And she had such a high fever. We tried everything.
Tenía tanta fiebre, lo intentamos todo.
It didn't look like it was going to work.
Parecía que nada le ayudaría.
Until we heard that 10 kilometers away there was a doctor, who was
Hasta que supimos que a 10 kilómetros había un médico que podía...
looking at people and giving them meds.
que ayudaba a gente y daba medicamentos.
Now I put my sister on my back -- burning --
Me puse a mi hermana en la espalda. Estaba ardiendo.
and I walked 10 kilometers with her strapped on my back.
Caminé 10 kilómetros con ella a mi espalda.
It was really hot. I was very hungry.
Hacía muchísimo calor. Tenía mucha hambre.
I was scared because I knew her life depended on my getting to this woman.
Tenía miedo. Sabía que su vida dependía de que llegara hasta aquella mujer.
We heard there was a woman doctor who was treating people.
Oímos que había una médico que trataba a la gente.
I walked 10 kilometers, putting one foot in front of the other.
Andé como pude los 10 kilómetros.
I got there and I saw huge crowds.
Llegué y vi multitud de gente.
Almost a thousand people were there, trying to break down the door.
Había más de mil personas intentando tirar la puerta abajo.
She was doing this in a church. How was I going to get in?
Trataba a la gente en una iglesia. ¿Cómo iba a entrar?
I had to crawl in between the legs of these people
Gateé entre las piernas de la gente
with my sister strapped on my back, find a way to a window.
con mi hermana atada a la espalda. Encontré una ventana.
And while they were trying to break down the door,
Mientras la gente intentaba tirar la puerta abajo,
I climbed in through the window, and jumped in.
trepé por la ventana y salté dentro.
This woman told me it was in the nick of time.
La mujer me dijo que había llegado justo a tiempo.
By the time we jumped into that hall, she was barely moving.
Cuando saltamos dentro, ella ya casi no se movía.
She gave a shot of her chloroquine -- what I learned was the chloroquine then --
Le inyectó cloroquina (entonces supe lo que era la cloroquina),
gave her some -- it must have been a re-hydration --
le dio un poco para rehidratarle,
and some other therapies, and put us in a corner.
y otras medicinas y nos puso en una esquina.
In about two to three hours, she started to move.
El cabo de dos o tres horas empezó a moverse.
And then they toweled her down because she started sweating,
La envolvieron en una toalla, pues empezó a sudar,
which was a good sign.
lo que era una buena señal.
And then my sister woke up.
Y por fin mi hermana se despertó.
And about five or six hours later, she said we could go home.
5 o 6 horas más tarde nos dijo que podíamos volver a casa.
I strapped her on my back.
Me la até a la espalda.
I walked the 10 kilometers back and it was the shortest walk I ever had.
Caminé los 10 kilómetros de vuelta y fue el paseo más corto de mi vida.
I was so happy -- (Applause) -- that my sister was alive!
¡Estaba tan feliz (Aplausos) por ver a mi hermana con vida!
Today she's 41 years old, a mother of three,
Hoy tiene 41 años y es madre de tres niños,
and she's a physician saving other lives.
y es un médico que salva vidas.
Why am I telling that? I'm telling you that because -- when it is you or your person involved --
¿Por qué os cuento esto? Os lo cuento porque si eres tú, o alguien cercano a ti,
you don't care where -- whether it's aid.
te da igual de dónde venga la ayuda.
You don't care what it is! (Applause)
¡No te importa lo que sea! (Aplausos)
You just want the person to be alive!
¡Tan sólo... tan sólo quieres que esa persona viva!
And now let me become less sentimental, and say that saving lives --
Dejadme que os diga de forma menos sentimental que el salvar vidas,
which some of the aid we get does on this continent -- when you save the life of anyone, a farmer, a teacher, a mother,
que es lo que hace parte de la ayuda en este continente, la vida de cualquiera: un granjero, un profesor, una madre...
they are contributing productively into the economy.
contribuye de forma productiva en la economía.
And as an economist, we can also look at that side of the story.
Como economista, también miro esa parte de la historia.
These are people who are productive agents in the economy.
Estas personas son agentes productivos en la economía.
So if we save people from HIV/AIDS, if we save them from malaria, it means they can form the base of production for our economy.
Por lo que si salvamos a la gente con VIH/SIDA o con malaria, pueden formar parte de la base productiva de nuestra economía.
And by the same token --
Y de la misma manera,
as someone said yesterday -- if we don't and they die,
como dijo alguien ayer, si los dejamos y mueren,
their children will become a burden on the economy.
sus hijos serán una carga para nuestra economía.
So even from an economic standpoint,
Así que incluso desde un punto de vista económico
if we leave the social and the humanitarian,
apartando lo social y humanitario,
we need to save lives now. So that's one of the reasons, from a personal experience, that I say
debemos salvar vidas ahora. Esta es una de las razones, desde mi experiencia, por la que digo:
let's channel these resources we get into something productive.
canalicemos los recursos que recibimos hacia algo productivo.
However, I will also tell you that I'm one of those
Sin embargo, también os diré que soy
who doesn't believe that this is the sole answer.
de las que no cree en una solución única.
That's why I said the debate has to get more sophisticated.
Por eso he dicho que el debate ha de ser más sofisticado.
You know, we have to use it well.
Tenemos que aprovecharlo bien.
What has happened in Europe?
¿Qué ha pasado en Europa?
Do you all know that Spain -- part of the EU --
¿Sabíais que España, miembro de la UE,
got 10 billion dollars in aid from the rest of the EU?
recibió 10 mil millones de dólares en ayudas de la UE?
Resources that were transferred to them --
Recursos que les fueron transferidos,
and were the Spanish ashamed of this? No!
¿se avergonzaron los españoles? ¡No!
The EU transferred 10 billion. Where did they use it?
¿En qué emplearon los 10 millones?
Have you been to southern Spain lately? There are roads everywhere.
¿Habéis ido hace poco al sur de España? Hay carreteras por todas partes.
Infrastructure everywhere.
Infraestructura en todos lados.
It is on the back of this that the whole of southern Spain
Gracias a esto, todo el sur de España
has developed into a services economy.
se ha convertido en una economía de servicios.
Did you know that Ireland got 3 billion dollars in aid?
¿Sabíais que Irlanda recibió 3 mil millones de dolares en ayudas?
Ireland is one of the fastest-growing economies in the European Union today.
Hoy Irlanda es una de las economías de crecimiento más rápido de la UE.
For which many people, even from other parts of the world,
Por lo que muchas personas de todo el mundo,
are going there to find jobs.
van allí en busca de trabajo.
What did they do with the 3 billion dollars in aid?
¿Qué hicieron con los 3 mil millones en ayudas?
They used it to build an information superhighway,
Construyeron una súper autopista de la información,
gain infrastructure that
aumentaron infraestructura que les permitió...
enables them to participate in the
les permitió participar en la
information technology revolution,
revolución de la tecnología de la información.
and to create jobs in their economy. They didn't say, "No, you know, we're not going to take this."
Y por eso, crearon trabajo en su economía. No dijeron que no querían la ayuda.
Today, the European Union is busy transferring aid.
Hoy, la UE no para de transferir ayudas.
My frustration is if they can build infrastructure in Spain --
Mi frustración es que si pueden construir infraestructuras en España,
which is roads, highways, other things that they can build --
tales como carreteras, autopistas y otras cosas,
I say then, why do they refuse to use the same aid
¿por qué no quieren utilizar la misma ayuda
to build the same infrastructure in our countries? (Applause)
para construir la misma infraestructura en nuestros países?
When we ask them and tell them what we need,
Si es eso lo que les decimos que necesitamos.
one of my worries today is that we have many foundations now.
Una de mis preocupaciones es que tenemos muchas fundaciones.
Now we talk about the World Bank, IMF, and accountability, all that
Hablamos del Banco Mundial, del FMI, de la responsabilidad...
and the EU.
y de la UE.
We also have private citizens now who have a lot of money --
También tenemos ciudadanos con mucho dinero.
some of them in this audience, with private foundations. And one day, these foundations have so much money,
Algunos están en este auditorio, y tienen fundaciones privadas. Y un día, esas fundaciones con tanto dinero,
they will overtake the official aid that is being given.
superarán la ayuda oficial que se está dando.
But I fear -- and I'm very grateful to all of them
Pero tengo miedo, y les estoy muy agradecida
for what they are trying to do on the continent --
por lo que intentan hacer en el continente,
but I'm also worried. I wake up with a gnawing in my belly because I see a new set of aid entrepreneurs on the continent.
pero me preocupa. Me despierto con un mal presentimiento. Veo emprendedores con ayudas en el continente.
And they're also going from country to country,
Y van de un país a otro,
and many times trying to find what to do.
muchas veces buscando qué hacer.
But I'm not really sure that their assistance
Pero no estoy segura de que su asistencia
is also being channeled in the right way.
esté siendo canalizada adecuadamente.
And many of them are not really familiar with the continent.
Muchos de ellos no están familiarizados con el continente.
They are just discovering.
Lo están descubriendo.
And many times I don't see Africans working with them.
Y muchas veces no veo africanos trabajando con ellos.
They are just going alone! (Applause) And many times I get the impression that they are not really even interested
¡Van por su cuenta! (Aplausos) Muchas veces tengo la impresión de que ni les interesa
in hearing from Africans who might know.
escuchar a los africanos que pueden saber.
They want to visit us,
Quieren venir de visita,
see what's happening on the ground and make a decision.
ver lo que pasa en el terreno y tomar una decisión.
And now I'm maybe being harsh.
Puede que esté siendo dura.
But I worry because this money is so important.
Pero estoy preocupada pues ese dinero es muy importante.
Now, who are they accountable to?
¿Ante quién son responsables?
Are we on their boards when they make decisions
¿Estamos en las directivas cuando toman decisiones
about where to channel money? Are we there?
sobre dónde canalizar el dinero? ¿Estamos ahí?
Will we make the same mistake that we made before?
¿Cometeremos otra vez el mismo error?
Have our presidents and our leaders -- everyone is talking about --
Alguna vez nuestros presidentes, de los que todo el mundo habla,
have they ever called these people together and said,
han reunido a toda esta gente y le han dicho,
"Look, your foundation and your foundation --
"Miren, su fundación y la suya,
you have so much money, we are grateful.
traen mucho dinero. Estamos muy agradecidos.
Let's sit down and really tell you where the money should be channeled
Sentémonos y les diremos adónde debería ir el dinero,
and where this aid should go."
adónde debería llegar esta ayuda."
Have we done that? The answer is no.
¿Lo hemos hecho? La respuesta es no.
And each one is making their own individual effort.
Cada cual hace su esfuerzo de forma individual.
And then 10 years from now, billions will again have gone into Africa,
En 10 años habrán entrado miles de millones en África,
and we would still have the same problems.
pero seguiremos con los mismos problemas.
This is what gives us the hopeless image.
Esto es lo que nos deja sin esperanzas.
Our inability to take charge and say to all these people bringing their money,
Nuestra falta de capacidad de sentar a la gente que trae dinero y decirles:
"Sit down."
"Siéntense."
And we don't do it because there are so many of us. We don't coordinate. We've not called the Bill Gates, and the Soros,
Y no lo hacemos porque somos muchos. No nos coordinamos. No hemos llamado a Bill Gates ni a Soros,
and everybody else who is helping and say,
ni al resto de los que están ayudando y no hemos dicho:
"Sit down. Let's have a conference with you.
"Vamos a mantener una reunión con vosotros.
As a continent, here are our priorities.
Como continente tenemos estas prioridades.
Here is where we want you to channel this money."
Esto es para lo que queremos utilizar el dinero."
Each one should not be an entrepreneur
No todos deberían ser emprendedores
going out and finding what is best.
que van en busca de lo que es mejor.
We're not trying to stop them at all! But to help them help us better. And what is disappointing me is that we are not doing this.
No queremos detenerles. Para nada. Queremos ayudarles a que nos ayuden. Y lo que me decepciona es que no estamos haciendo nada de esto.
Ten years from now we will have the same story,
Dentro de 10 años estaremos hablando de lo mismo,
and we will be repeating the same things. So our problem right now is, how can we leverage
repetiremos las mismas cosas que hoy. Así que el problema es cómo podemos aprovechar
all this good will that is coming towards our way?
todas estas buenas acciones que nos están llegando.
How can we get government to combine properly
Cómo conseguir que el se gobierno combine adecuadamente
with these private foundations, with the international organizations,
con las fundaciones privadas, las organizaciones internacionales
and with our private sector.
y con nuestro sector privado.
I firmly believe in that private sector thing too.
Creo firmemente en el sector privado.
But it cannot do it alone.
Pero no lo pueden hacer solos.
So there might be a few ideas we could think of that could work. They said this is about proliferating and sharing ideas.
Podemos pensar en algunas ideas que hagan que esto funcione. Estos encuentros son para compartir y difundir ideas.
So why don't we think of using some of this aid?
¿Por qué no pensamos en aprovechar parte de la ayuda?
Well, why don't we first say to those helping us out,
Mejor aún, por que no les decimos a los que nos ayudan:
"Don't be shy about infrastructure.
¡No temáis a la infraestructura!
That health that you're working on cannot be sustainable without infrastructure. That education will work better
La sanidad no se mantendrá si no tenemos infraestructuras. La educación será mejor
if we've got electricity and railroads, and so on.
si tenemos electricidad y carreteras, y otras cosas.
That agriculture will work better if there are railroads to get the goods to market.
La agricultura mejorará con carreteras por las que llevar los productos al mercado.
Don't be shy of it.
¡No la despreciéis!
Invest some of your resources in that, too."
Invertid parte de vuestros recursos en ella.
And then we can see that this is one combination
Veremos como esto es una combinación
of private, international, multilateral money,
del dinero privado, internacional, multilateral,
private sector and the African that we can put together as a partnership,
del sector privado y de los africanos y podemos asociarnos
so that aid can be a facilitator.
para que la ayuda sea ayuda.
That is all aid can be.
Eso es la ayuda.
Aid cannot solve our problems, I'm firmly convinced about that.
La ayuda no resolverá nuestros problemas. Estoy totalmente convencida.
But it can be catalytic. And if we fail to use it as catalytic,
Pero puede ser catalítica, y si la usamos de otra manera
we would have failed. One of the reasons why China is a bit popular with Africans now --
habremos fracasado. Una razón por la que China goza de simpatía en África
one of the reasons is not only just that, you know, these people are stupid
una de las razones, no es por aquello de: esa gente es tonta
and China is coming to take resources.
y China viene a llevarse recursos.
It's because there's a little more leverage in terms of the Chinese.
Es porque podemos aprovechar mejor la ayuda de los chinos.
If you tell them, "We need a road here,"
Si les dices: "Aquí necesitamos una carretera"
they will help you build it.
ellos te ayudan a construirla.
They don't shy away from infrastructure.
No les asustan las infraestructuras.
In fact, the Chinese minister of finance said to me,
De hecho, el ministro de Finanzas chino me dijo,
when I asked him what are we doing wrong in Nigeria.
cuando le pregunté qué hacíamos mal en Nigeria.
He said, "There are two things you need only.
Tan sólo se necesitan dos cosas:
Infrastructure, infrastructure, infrastructure and discipline.
Infraestructura, infraestructura, infraestructura... y disciplina.
You are undisciplined." (Applause)
Sois indisciplinados. (Aplausos)
And I repeat it for the continent.
Y se lo repito al continente.
It's the same. We need infrastructure, infrastructure and discipline.
Es lo mismo, necesitamos infraestructura y disciplina.
So we can make a catalytic to help us provide some of that.
Podemos hacer un catalizador que nos ayude a conseguir algo de eso.
Now I realize -- I'm not saying -- health and education --
Pero, no me refiero a que la salud y la educación
no, you can also provide that as well.
se dejen de lado, hay que procurarlas también.
But I'm saying it's not either or.
No digo que sea una cosa u otra.
Let's see how aid can be a facilitator in partnership.
Asociémonos para las ayudas.
One idea.
Esto es una idea.
Second thing, for the private sector, people are afraid to take risks on the continent.
Otra idea, para el sector privado. La gente tiene miedo de arriesgarse en el continente.
Why can't some of this aid be used as a kind of guarantee mechanisms,
Porqué no utilizar ayudas para generar un mecanismo de garantía,
to enable people to take risk? (Applause)
que permita a la gente asumir riesgos. (Aplausos)
And finally, because they are both standing at my -- I'm out of time.
Por último, porque ambos están... He agotado el tiempo.
Am I out of time? OK, so let me not forget my punchline.
¿Se me ha acabado el tiempo? Vale, no quiero olvidarme de lo más importante.
One of the things I want everybody to collaborate on is
Una de las cosas en las que quiero que todos colaboren es
to support women, to create jobs. (Applause)
en apoyar a la mujer, en crear empleos. (Aplausos)
A lot has been said here about women, I don't need to repeat it.
Se han dicho muchas cosas sobre la mujer, no es necesario repetirlo.
But there are people -- women -- creating jobs. And we know, studies have shown
Pero hay personas, mujeres, que están creando empleos. Y sabemos, por lo que los estudios muestran
that when you put resources in the hand of the woman --
que cuando pones recursos en las manos de una mujer,
in fact, there's an econometric study,
sobre esto hay un estudio econométrico,
the World Bank Review, done in 2000, showing that transfers into the hands of women result
un informe del Banco Mundial del año 2000, que muestra que las transferencias a mujeres daban como resultado
in healthier children, more for the household, more for the economy and all that.
niños más sanos, mejoras para la casa y para la economía.
So I'm saying that one of the takeaways from here --
Lo que digo es que una de las lecturas que tenemos que sacar de aquí,
I'm not saying the men are not important --
no digo que los hombres no sean importantes,
obviously, if you leave the husbands out, what will they do?
obviamente, si quitas a los maridos, ¿qué harían?
They'll come back home and get disgruntled,
Al volver a casa se disgustarían,
and it will result in difficulties we don't want.
y generaría dificultades que no queremos.
We don't want men beating their wives
No queremos que los hombres peguen a sus mujeres
because they don't have a job, and so on.
por no tener trabajo y esas cosas.
But at the margin, we also -- I want to push this,
Pero al margen, queremos, yo quiero resaltarlo
because the reason is the men automatically --
pues la razón es, los hombres automáticamente
they get -- not automatically, but they tend to get more support.
reciben casi siempre más apoyo.
But I want you to realize that resources
Quiero que se den cuenta que los recursos
in the hands of African women is a powerful tool.
en manos de la mujer africana es una herramienta potente.
There are people creating jobs.
Hay gente creando empleo,
Beatrice Gakuba has created 200 jobs from her flower business in Rwanda.
Beatrice Gakuba ha creado 200 puestos en su negocio de flores en Ruanda.
We have Ibukun Awosika in Nigeria, with the chair company.
Tenemos a Ibukun Awosika en Nigeria, con los muebles, la empresa de sillas.
She wants to expand.
Quiere expandirse.
She needs another 20 million. She will create another 100, 200 more jobs.
Necesita 20 millones más. Creará 100 o 200 puestos de trabajo más.
So take away from here is how are you going to put together
A partir de ahora pensad cómo unificar
the resources to put money in the hands of women in the middle who are ready --
los recursos en manos de mujeres que están a mitad camino, que están preparadas:
business people who want to expand and create more jobs.
son empresarios que quieren expandirse y crear más trabajo.
And lastly, what are you going to do
Y por último, ¿qué vais a hacer
to be part of this partnership of aid, government, private sector
para formar parte de esta asociación de ayudas, gobierno, sector privado
and the African as an individual? Thank you. (Applause)
y los africanos como individuos? Gracias. (Aplausos)